Guide to the Manhattan Graphics Center 9/11 Print Portfolio 2001-2002 PR 257
New-York Historical Society
Manhattan Graphics Center 9/11 Print Portfolio
2001-2002
New-York Historical Society
PR 257
1.34 Linear feet (1 box)
Collection of art prints from the Manhattan Graphics Center relating to the events of 9/11. Includes engravings, silkscreens, etchings, lithographs, and other printmaking processes.
Provenance
Gift of Manhattan Graphics Center, 2003.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Historical Note
The Manhattan Graphics Center opened in 1986 as an artist-run studio and gallery space. They offer both classes and studio access to printmakers, who volunteer as staff. The Manhattan Graphics Center also shows exhibitions by artists who use the space.
The Manhattan Graphics Center is located very close to Ground Zero, one block east of the West Side Highway, north of Canal Street and south of Spring Street. Some of the artists whose work is in the portfolio were at the Manhattan Graphics Center on the morning of 9/11. The neighborhood that the Manhattan Graphics Center is in was surrounded by clean up activity and the presence of rescue workers after the event. Members also had personal connections to 9/11, through family members and colleagues.
In the spring of 2002, Vijay Kumar, a member and teacher at the Manhattan Graphics Center, created the concept for the collection, which allowed the Center's artists to respond to the events of 9/11. An exhibition of the works opened on September 11, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The Manhattan Graphics Center 9/11 Print Portfolio Collection spans the period from 2001 to 2002 and primarily contains prints related to the events of 9/11. The collection consists of 43 prints, all in vertical format. Each image is part of an edition of 5 or more. The paper that the images are printed on was formatted to approximately 20 x 15 inches. The techniques used in this collection range from etching, silkscreen, lithograph, photo transfer, woodcut, and drypoint, among others.
The subject matter of the Manhattan Graphics Center 9/11 Print Portfolio Collection is primarily the artists' personal connections to and the things that they observed in the months after the events of 9/11. The works contain images of missing person flyers, death and destruction, media coverage, memorials, rescue workers, and the towers themselves.
The Collection contains prints by the following artists: Anneli Arms, Cynthia Back, Miriam Bell, Bonnie Blitstein, Val Britton, Ruth Bugzester, Kit Callahan, Julia Foote, Beth Ganz, Monika E. De Vries Gohlke, Shoshanna Golin, Jody Gorton, Florrie Gotlib, Kristen Gregory, Sarah Hauser, Nicholas Hill, Carmen Isasi, Vijay Kumar, Annette Lilleskov, Lynn Margileth, Meredith Mayer, Judy Mensch, Diane Miller, Majorie Miller, Donald Murphy, Lily Ng, Hilary North, Margaret Nussbaum, Joseph A. Osina, Sarah Plimpton, Francesca Samsel, Larry Schulte Marilyn Silberstang, Sigrid Sperzel, Barbara Spiller, Sandy Sykes, David Thomas, Gwenn Thomas, Marina Tsesarskaya, William Tucker, Angela Valeria, Loretta Waite, and Caroline Waloski.
Arrangement
Prints are arranged alphabetically by artist.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional material related to 9/11 can be found in the Here is New York Collection (PR 258) and the World Trade Center Photograph Collection (PR 169).
World Trade Center Site (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Prints (visual works).; Etchings (prints); Drypoints (prints); New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Lithographs.; Woodcuts (prints); Photomechanical prints.; Photogravures; Artistic collaboration; Printmakers; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Art.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Pictorial works.; Terrorism -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Victims of terrorism -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Margileth, Lynn; Mayer, Meredith; Mensch, Judy; Miller, Diane; Miller, Marjorie; Murphy, Donald; Ng, Lily; North, Hilary; Nussbaum, Margaret; Osina, Joseph A.; Plimpton, Sarah; Samsel, Francesca; Schulte, Larry; Silberstang, Marilyn; Sperzel, Sigrid; Spiller, Barbara; Sykes, Sandy; Thomas, David; Thomas, Gwenn; Tsesarskaya, Marina; Tucker, William; Valeria, Angela; Waite, Loretta; Waloski, Caroline; Arms, Anneli, 1935 -; Back, Cynthia; Bell, Miriam; Blitstein, Bonnie; Britton, Val, 1977-; Bugzester, Ruth; Callahan, Kit; Foote, Julia; Ganz, Beth; Gohlke, Monkia E. De Vries; Golin, Shoshanna; Gorton, Judy; Gotlib, Florrie; Gregory, Kristen; Hauser, Sarah; Hill, Nicholas; Isasi Martínez, Carmen; Kumar, Vijay; Lilleskov, Annette; World Trade Center (New York, N.Y.: 1970-2001)
- Series I: Prints
  Scope and Contents note
  - ARMS, Anneli, 1935 -
    - Playground Revisited, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Soft ground etching with Carborundum, (3/11), Image: 19 7/8 x 10 1/16 in.
  - BACK, Cynthia
    - It was Reported Over and Over, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Etching, (3/5), Image: 14 1/8 x 9 15/16 in.
  - BELL, Miriam
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Collograph, (1/5), Image: 10 5/6 x 9 in.
  - BLITSTEIN, Bonnie
    - 9/11, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Silkscreen, (2/5), Image: 19 x 10 in.
  - BRITTON, Val
    - Fear of that In-Between Space, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Etching and chine colle, (6/6), Image: 12 1/2 x 9 3/16 in.
  - BUGZESTER, Ruth
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Drypoint, Image: 17 3/4 x 11 7/8 in.
  - CALLAHAN, Kit
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Etching, (1/25), Image: 8 7/8 x 6 in.
  - FOOTE, Julia
    - Us and Them, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Color Xerox transfer, (5/10), Image: 8 3/4 x 12 3/8 in.
  - GANZ, Beth
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Photogravure, (3/10), Image: 13 3/4 x 10 3/16 in.
  - GOHLKE, Monika E. De Vries
    - In Memoriam, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Etching, (4/5), Image: 8 7/8 x 5 7/8 in.
  - GOLIN, Shoshanna
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Photo etching, (5/5), Image: 10 3/8 x 7 7/16 in.
  - GORTON, Judy Burst
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Viscosity etching, (2/12), Image: 8 7/8 x 8 7/8 in.
  - GOTLIB, Florence
    - War, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Spit bite etching, (3/5), Image: 6 7/8 x 6 15/16 in.
  - GREGORY, Kristen
    - Untitled, 5/2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Etching, photo transfer, and chine colle, (2/12), Image: 9 9/16 x 7 in.
  - HAUSER, Sarah
    - Jake, Rescue Dog, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Woodcut, (38/100), Image: 9 5/6 x 8 1/8 in.
  - HILL, Nicholas
    - Indelible, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Drypoint, Image: 9 x 5 5/6 in.
  - ISASI, Carmen
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Lithograph, Image: 12 3/4 x 9 1/2 in.
  - KUMAR, Vijay
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Etching, (A/P), Image: 10 1/4 x 13 3/4 in.
  - LILLESKOV, Annette
    - 9/11 Rain of Terror, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Soft ground etching, (3/10), Image: 11 7/8 x 8 7/8 in.
  - MARGILETH, Lynn
    - Each Star, a Loved One, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Etching, (9/12), Image: 11 13/16 x 8 7/8 in.
  - MAYER, Meredith
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Silkscreen, (1/7), Image: 20 1/8 x 15 1/8 in.
  - MENSCH, Judy
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Lithograph, (5/8), Image: 4 9/16 x 3 15/16 in.
  - MILLER, Diane
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      [Woodcut, etching, and relief], (9/11), Image: 19 15/16 x 14 7/8 in.
  - MILLER, Marjorie
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Photo etching, (4/10), Image: 8 1/4 x 6 in.
  - MURPHY, Donald
    - Missing, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      [Silicone intaglio], (3/14), Image: 9 15/16 x 8 in.
  - NG, Lily
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Etching and aquatint, (4/5), Image: 20 1/8 x 14 7/8 in.
  - NORTH, Hilary
    - Ghost, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Linoleum cut, Ghost print, (2/5), Image: 16 1/2 x 5 5/8 in.
  - NUSSBAUM, Margaret
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Silkscreen, (2/14), Image: 20 1/4 x 15 1/8 in.
  - OSINA, Joseph A.
    - Nine Eleven, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Monotype, Image: 13 x 6 15/16 in.
  - PLIMPTON, Sarah
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Etching, (4/5), Image: 11 7/8 x 9 in.
  - SAMSEL, Francesca
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Viscosity etching, Image: 12 15/16 x 7 1/4 in.
  - SCHULTE, Larry
    - WTC - Then, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Color Xerox transfer, Image: 12 11/16 x 7 13/16 in.
  - SILBERSTANG, Marilyn
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Etching, (4/5), Image: 15 1/2 x 9 15/16 in.
  - SPERZEL, Sigrid
    - Untitled, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Soft ground etching with Xerox transfer, (3/13), Image: 9 3/16 x 6 1/8 in.
  - SPILLER, Barbara
    - 9/11, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Etching, (2/5), Image: 14 3/4 x 6 in.
  - SYKES, Sandy
    - three-9-11, [2002] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Woodcut, (3/5), Image: 20 1/4 x 11 5/8 in.
  - THOMAS, David
    - To the Exit, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      [Linocut], (3/5), Image: 9 x 12 in.
  - THOMAS, Gwenn
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      [Silkscreen], (4/5), Image: 16 3/4 x 12 in.
  - TSESARSKAYA, Marina
    - Opportunity Conversation 5, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Photo transfer and embossing, (A/P), Image: 11 7/16 x 4 3/8 in.
  - TUCKER, William
    - Flight of Demons, (1st State), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Etching, (4/10), Image: 11 3/8 x 8 15/16 in.
  - VALERIA, Angela
    - Hug, 5/2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Lithograph, (4/5), Image: 20 x 15 in.
  - WAITE, Loretta
    - September 11, 2001 and Six Months Later, 5/2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Color Xerox transfer, (1/5), Image: 11 x 7 3/4 in.
  - WALOSKI, Caroline
    - Untitled, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Etching and chine colle, (3/22), Image: 14 3/8 x 14 7/8 in.